Guide to the World War I Pamphlets and Bulletins MS 027
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
World War I Pamphlets, Bulletins and Miscellanea
1917-1921, (Bulk 1917-1918)
1917-1918
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Western Connecticut State University. Archives and Special Collections Library
MS 027
156
7.75 Linear Feet, 4 boxes 1 bound volume, and 1 OS Folder
The collection includes material published by the Committee on Public Information (CPI) and a variety of propagandistic and commemorative materials published during and around the time of the First World War.
Provenance
The provenance of much of this material is unknown. The Official Bulletin series was donated by the Pequot Library, Pequot, CT. This is an artificial collection and WWI materials are added to this collection as they are acquired. The WCSU Archives has another similar collection, World War I Era Propaganda and Publications, which was collected by an individual involved in fundraising for the Allies and advocacy for U.S. intervention.
Access Restrictions
Some of this material is brittle and may not be handled. Access to some material is subject to the judement of the archivist.
Historical/Biographical Note
When America entered World War I on April 6, 1917, unwavering public support was considered to be crucial to the entire wartime effort. On April 13, 1917, President Wilson created the Committee on Public Information (CPI) to promote the war domestically while publicizing American war aims abroad. Under the leadership of George Creel the CPI began publishing the Red, White and Blue Series, which expanded speeches by Wilson into patriotic rhetoric while attacking Germany under titles such as German War Practices and Conquest and Kultur. The War Information Series contains messages with notes explaining in further detail the events that led up to World War I. The daily Official Bulletin, which was published from May 19, 1917 to August 16, 1918, contained government news.
Other items included in this collection are ephemera from the period and publications to commemorate the War.
Scope and Content Note
This collection is organized into 5 series: 1. Red, White and Blue Series; 2. War Information Series; 3. Miscellaneous; 4. Lorenz Collection of World War I Autographs; 5. Official Bulletin
The "miscellaneous" series includes: Collier's New Photographic History of World's War which is comprised of sketches, drawings and paintings of personalities, regiments, and battlefields made by artists at the front (130pgs). Photographs by the official photographers accompanying each army collected and arranged by Francis J. Reynolds and C. W. Taylor. 1919. It also includes ongoing acquisitions that document propagandistic efforts during the War.
For the Official Bulletin, topical indexes exist for issues published from January 2, 1918, through October 31, 1918. Researchers should note there are several gaps exist within the chronology of this series.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically or chronologically within each series.
The files are grouped into 5 series:
Missing Title
1. Red, White and Blue Series
2. War Information Series
3. Miscellaneous
4. Lorenz Collection of WW I Autographs
5. Official Bulletin
Fliers (printed matter); Photographs.; United States -- History -- World War, 1939-1945.; Publications.; Pamphlets; World War, 1914-1918 -- United States; World War, 1914-1918 -- Propaganda; World War, 1914-1918 -- Pictorial works; World War, 1914-1918 -- United States -- Periodicals; Creel, George, 1876-1953.; Committee on Public Information.
- 1. Red, White and Blue Series, 46597
  - The Battle Line of Democracy-Prose and Poetry of the World War., 1917; 46607 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Conquest and Kultur-Aims of the Germans in Their Own Words, edited by Wallace Notestein and Elmer E. Stoll., 1918; 46606 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - German Plots and Intrigues in the U.S. During Its Neutrality by E. E. Sperry and Willis M. West., 1918; 46605 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - German Treatment of Conquered Territory: Part II of German War Practices; being Part II of German War Practices., 1918; 46604 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - German War Practices: Part 1, Treatment of Civilians, edited by Dana C.Munro, George C. Sellery and August C. Krey, 1918; 46603 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - National Service Handbook., 1917; 46602 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The President's Flag Day Address with evidence of Germany's Plans., undated; 46601 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - June 14, 1917., 46600 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - War Cyclopedia; A handbook for ready reference on the Great War., 1918; 46599 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - War, Labor and Peace; Some Recent Addresses and Writings of President Wilson., 1918; 46598 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- 2. War Information Series, 46588
  - #1: The War Message and the Facts Behind It. Annotated text of President Wilson's message April 2, 1917., 1917-1918; 46596 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - #2: The Nation in Arms by Franklin K. Lane and Newton D. Baker., 1917; 46595 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - #11: The German War Code by George W. Scott and James W. Garner., 1918; 46594 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - #12: American and Allied Ideals by Stuart P. Sherman., 1918; 46593 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - #13: German Militarism and Its German Critics by Charles Altschul., 1918; 46592 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - #14: The War for Peace by Arthur D. Call, Secretary of the American Peace Society., 1918; 46591 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - #15: Why America Fights Germany by John S. P. Tatlock., 1918; 46590 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - #16: Study of the Great War by Samuel B. Harding., 1918; 46589 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- 3. Miscellaneous, 46581
  - Documents Relating to WW I. Translated from the Italian by Thomas Okey., undated; 46587 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - International Conciliation. Documents Regarding the European War. Series No.XV. The Entry of the United States, 1917; 46586 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Shall We Commit Suicide by The Rt. Hon. Winston S. Churchill., undated; 46585 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - What Young People Ought to Know About War and Peace by Lucia Ames Mead., undated; 46584 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Collier's New Photographic History of World's War, 1919; 46583 (Box 4)
  - The Stars and Stripes: a complete file of the Stars and Stripes, printed in France from February 8th 1918 to June 13th 1919, 46582 (Item 1)
    General note
    Title also listed in WCSU's online catalog. This volume was added to the collection in 2007.
  - Over the Top for you, buy U.S. Gov't Bonds: Third Liberty Loan, 1918; 59014 (Folder OS Folder 2.1)
  - Les fils et le foyers de la belgique, Postcard, ca.1916; 59015 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Erwischt und gefangen, Postcard, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    General
    By Arthur Thiele. Verso - Es zogen tommies und franzos Auf Schleichpatroulle nachtlicht los, die maske jeder vorm Gesicht; wem graut bei diesem Anblick nicht? Jedoch den deutschen kriegersmann Ficht solche Spukgestalt nicht an, Eh' sich die Bande druber klar "Entlarvt" sie und gefangen war. (Trans. Tommies and Frenchies set off on a stealth night patrol, the mask on everyone's face; Who does not dread the sight? However, the German warrior man does not attack such haunting figures, before the gang was clearly "unmasked" and captured.
  - Their Crimes (booklet), 1917 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Published by Casswell and Company. Chapters include: Robbery, Incendiarism, Murder, Outrages on Women and Children, Killing the Wounded, Sheltering behind Women, etc.
  - In France, we'll make him dance, Postcard, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 18.1)
- 4. Lorenz Collection of WW I Autographs, 46578
  - The Story of the Lorenz Collection of World War Autographs and of the Marshall Folk Victory-Harmony Banner by William Albert Lorenz., 1921; 46580 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Catalog of the Lorenz Collection of World War Autographs by William Albert Lorenz., 1921; 46579 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- 5. Official Bulletin and Official U.S. Bulletin, 46574
  - Official Bulletin, 1917-1918; 46577 (Box 2, Folder *)
    30 September 1918: Extension of suffrage to women is vital to winning the war, President tells Senate
  - Official Bulletin, 1918; 46576 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Topical Index, January 2, 1918 - October 31, 1918., 46575 (Box 3, Folder 2)